<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Present Minutes - for everyday meditation</title>
    <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Present Minutes - for everyday meditation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 17:22:30 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 14:37:20 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/welcome/</guid>
      <description>How can we bring the benefits of meditation to the rest of our life?  That&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;m setting out to explore - and maybe help you, on your journey, too.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Navigating Anxiety</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/navigating-anxiety/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 17:22:30 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/navigating-anxiety/</guid>
      <description>Some practical tips for working with your anxiety</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: On Having No Head</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/on-having-no-head/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 16:40:20 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/on-having-no-head/</guid>
      <description>I recently re-read Douglas Hardings short book, &amp;ldquo;On Having No Head&amp;rdquo;. He wrote this classic in 1961, and I read it first as a young man perhaps 30 years ago, but it has not aged one drop. This is a true gem of a book - it sparkles in the light and when viewed from some angles it is beautiful indeed, but there are some sharp pointy bits, and it&amp;rsquo;s quite hard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Days Suck</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/some-days-suck/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 17:03:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/some-days-suck/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s face it, some days are pretty awful. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s something dramatic - you are laid off at work, or someone near to you is diagnosed with something really bad, or you return to your car to find a huge scrape all the way along one side and no note of apology under the windscreen wiper.
Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s something that might appear trivial to others - you tread on an errant piece of Lego and spill your cup of tea on your clean clothes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enjoying your chores</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/enjoying-your-chores/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/enjoying-your-chores/</guid>
      <description>We all have to do difficult things, but we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t just do them for the hoped-for outcome.  We can chose to do them mindfully, regardless of outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equanimity</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/equanimity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 17:04:25 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/equanimity/</guid>
      <description>Equanimity for Buddhists is one of the four highest emotions, one of the states we aspire to live in and live by.  We see it as the ground for wisdom, the protector of compassion and love, and as full of radiance and warmth for others.  It&amp;rsquo;s a quality we can consciously cultivate through meditation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Mind Illuminated</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/the-mind-illuminated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 16:52:46 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/the-mind-illuminated/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a book that will not just introduce you to meditation, but provide you with clear and careful instructions that will take you all the way from beginner to full on yogi, this is the book for you. It&amp;rsquo;s big - over 500 pages - but don&amp;rsquo;t let that put you off: that&amp;rsquo;s just because it&amp;rsquo;s covering a huge amount of ground.
Now, before we go any further, something needs to be said: the author of this tome, John Yates, aka Culadasa died recently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where Do You Go to My Lovely</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/where-do-you-go-to-my-lovely/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2023 12:03:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/where-do-you-go-to-my-lovely/</guid>
      <description>So sang Peter Starstedt, back in 1969 Although I&amp;rsquo;m too young to remember the song at release, it was none the less a frequent enough occurrence on the radio of my youth. The song, in a style described by its Wikipedia article as &amp;ldquo;faux European waltz tune&amp;hellip; with brief bursts of French-style accordion&amp;rdquo;, is still bringing in significant royalties for Mr Starstedt, decades after its release. The lyrics mention all sorts of things - Marlene Dietrich, Picasso, the Sorbonne, and Napoleon brandy among them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness - Want More?</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/happiness-want-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 17:15:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/happiness-want-more/</guid>
      <description>One of my favourite things about meditation is how I get to talk about happiness with people without it being childish. Happiness is, it seems to me, simply a good thing. Why wouldn&amp;rsquo;t people want to be happy more of the time?
Well most of us might, perhaps, but somehow we don&amp;rsquo;t think we can talk about it. It&amp;rsquo;s ridiculous, isn&amp;rsquo;t it, that when we talk about &amp;ldquo;being happy&amp;rdquo;, other people seem to regard us with a look that says we&amp;rsquo;re not a serious grown-up, but have instead reverted to a child-like state and are incapable of seeing all the bad stuff.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distraction</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/forget-then-remember/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/forget-then-remember/</guid>
      <description>The cycle of getting distracted and then returning to what we should have been attending to is ever-present in our lives.  Part of meditation is training to shorten this loop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeing not believing</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/seeing-is-not-believing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/seeing-is-not-believing/</guid>
      <description>I love optical illusions. This particular one shows our brain trying to make sense of perspective - the two horizontal boxes are the same width, but the top one looks wider than the bottom one because of what look like the &amp;ldquo;railway lines&amp;rdquo; behind them. There are lots of theories about what&amp;rsquo;s going on in our brains when we see things like this. But what we know for sure, is that our brain is telling us something about the world that isn&amp;rsquo;t true.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Humans are creatures of doubt</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/doubts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/doubts/</guid>
      <description>Buddhists talk about Doubt as one of the &amp;ldquo;five hindrances&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s important to distinguish between two different ways we use the English word doubt.
The first is helpful: it&amp;rsquo;s about inquiry, investigation, and examination. We shouldn&amp;rsquo;t automatically believe or disbelieve things we hear, we should be curious - that kind of doubt is helpful. That&amp;rsquo;s what the robin in today&amp;rsquo;s photo is doing: he is just thinking &amp;ldquo;is there anything I can eat here?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy Not Happy Christmas</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/happy-not-happy-christmas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 16:11:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/happy-not-happy-christmas/</guid>
      <description>Some days you just feel sad. Things might be going ok at work, the family are in truth at least somewhat lovely (all things considered), maybe it&amp;rsquo;s even stopped raining for twenty minutes and the sun has come out, but for whatever reason, you&amp;rsquo;re not feeling it at all. Maybe you were feeling ok yesterday, maybe yesterday wasn&amp;rsquo;t so good either, but today definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t up to the mark.
And you know what?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Around the Corner</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/around-the-corner/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Oct 2021 16:07:05 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/around-the-corner/</guid>
      <description>One of the wonders of Life is the constant unexpectedness of it all. A long time ago, when I was driving along a road I knew very well, and had driven for years, I came around a corner and was confronted by the sight of a very large pig, just standing in the middle of the road. I just about managed to avoid the embarrassment of a pig-related insurance claim, pulled over, and soon found that it had escaped from a nearby farm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crappy days - the Good and Bad</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/good-and-bad/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 15:49:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/good-and-bad/</guid>
      <description>What do you think of yourself in the world? How do you compare yourself to those around you? Do you remember all the bad things you&amp;rsquo;ve done in your life, all the mean things you said? Could you write a list of them? Is it a long list, or a very long one?
There are two answers to this: the first is that no, you can&amp;rsquo;t remember doing any bad things, and you&amp;rsquo;re a brilliant person.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Action in difficult times</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/action-for-difficult-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/action-for-difficult-times/</guid>
      <description>These are the difficult times. When we can make a difference, to ourselves and others, by what we do in the moment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overcast with clear spells</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/overcast-with-clear-spells/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2020 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/overcast-with-clear-spells/</guid>
      <description>Every day, we start the day with a certain set of expectations, and our own set of strengths and weaknesses to bring to bear on them.  Some days seem to work out ok, while others just seem to run off track, despite our best intentions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How we change all the time</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/we-are-always-changing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/we-are-always-changing/</guid>
      <description>One of the things you&amp;rsquo;ll recognise about yourself if you are at all self-aware is that you&amp;rsquo;re somewhat of a different person this year, compared to a few years ago. You&amp;rsquo;ve perhaps had a few knocks, maybe a couple of lucky breaks, and you&amp;rsquo;ve learned from these experiences, and you&amp;rsquo;ve changed. Some of this is going to be for the better, and some of it is likely for the worse - we all age, get sick, end up in a ridiculous fight with our loved ones about who&amp;rsquo;s turn it is to walk the dog in the rain or whatever.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
