<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Present Minutes on Present Minutes - for everyday meditation</title>
    <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Present Minutes on Present Minutes - for everyday meditation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 17:03:03 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://presentminutes.co.uk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Guided meditations</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/meditations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 12:32:25 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/meditations/</guid>
      <description>Here are some guided meditations that you might find useful for your own practice. Your browser will likely let you play them directly from this page, but you can also download the MP3 files and store them on your phone or media player to use at your convenience - click on the three dots at the right-hand end to download.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 14:37:20 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/welcome/</guid>
      <description>How can we bring the benefits of meditation to the rest of our life?  That&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;m setting out to explore - and maybe help you, on your journey, too.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Days Suck</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/some-days-suck/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 17:03:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/some-days-suck/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s face it, some days are pretty awful. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s something dramatic - you are laid off at work, or someone near to you is diagnosed with something really bad, or you return to your car to find a huge scrape all the way along one side and no note of apology under the windscreen wiper.
Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s something that might appear trivial to others - you tread on an errant piece of Lego and spill your cup of tea on your clean clothes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enjoying your chores</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/enjoying-your-chores/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/enjoying-your-chores/</guid>
      <description>We all have to do difficult things, but we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t just do them for the hoped-for outcome.  We can chose to do them mindfully, regardless of outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Levels of Mind</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/five-levels-of-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/five-levels-of-mind/</guid>
      <description>In his writings on meditation, the contemporary meditator and psuchologist Loch Kelly talks about five levels of mind: everyday mind, subtle mind, pure consciousness, awareness energy, and heart-mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equanimity</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/equanimity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 17:04:25 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/equanimity/</guid>
      <description>Equanimity for Buddhists is one of the four highest emotions, one of the states we aspire to live in and live by.  We see it as the ground for wisdom, the protector of compassion and love, and as full of radiance and warmth for others.  It&amp;rsquo;s a quality we can consciously cultivate through meditation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distraction</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/forget-then-remember/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2022 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/forget-then-remember/</guid>
      <description>The cycle of getting distracted and then returning to what we should have been attending to is ever-present in our lives.  Part of meditation is training to shorten this loop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeing not believing</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/seeing-is-not-believing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/seeing-is-not-believing/</guid>
      <description>I love optical illusions. This particular one shows our brain trying to make sense of perspective - the two horizontal boxes are the same width, but the top one looks wider than the bottom one because of what look like the &amp;ldquo;railway lines&amp;rdquo; behind them. There are lots of theories about what&amp;rsquo;s going on in our brains when we see things like this. But what we know for sure, is that our brain is telling us something about the world that isn&amp;rsquo;t true.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Humans are creatures of doubt</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/doubts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/doubts/</guid>
      <description>Buddhists talk about Doubt as one of the &amp;ldquo;five hindrances&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s important to distinguish between two different ways we use the English word doubt.
The first is helpful: it&amp;rsquo;s about inquiry, investigation, and examination. We shouldn&amp;rsquo;t automatically believe or disbelieve things we hear, we should be curious - that kind of doubt is helpful. That&amp;rsquo;s what the robin in today&amp;rsquo;s photo is doing: he is just thinking &amp;ldquo;is there anything I can eat here?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good and Bad</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/good-and-bad/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 15:49:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/good-and-bad/</guid>
      <description>What do you think of yourself in the world? How do you compare yourself to those around you? Do you remember all the bad things you&amp;rsquo;ve done in your life, all the mean things you said? Could you write a list of them? Is it a long list, or a very long one?
There are two answers to this: the first is that no, you can&amp;rsquo;t remember doing any bad things, and you&amp;rsquo;re a brilliant person.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Action in difficult times</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/action-for-difficult-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/action-for-difficult-times/</guid>
      <description>These are the difficult times. When we can make a difference, to ourselves and others, by what we do in the moment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overcast with clear spells</title>
      <link>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/overcast-with-clear-spells/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2020 17:04:43 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://presentminutes.co.uk/posts/overcast-with-clear-spells/</guid>
      <description>Every day, we start the day with a certain set of expectations, and our own set of strengths and weaknesses to bring to bear on them.  Some days seem to work out ok, while others just seem to run off track, despite our best intentions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
